Finding Aid for St. Thomas Episcopal Church, Detroit, Mich., Records 1885-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Thomas Episcopal Church, Detroit, Mich., Records 1885-1998
St. Thomas Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
3 linear ft. (5 boxes)
Church established as mission Sunday School in 1884 and disbanded in 1988 because of declining membership. Registers of baptisms, marriages, burials and communicants; registers of church services; vestry minutes, annual parish meeting minutes, bishop's committee minutes, correspondence, budgets and treasurer's annual reports, and photograph albums.
9414 Ba 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was part of a larger accession (Donor No. 1059 ) received from the Episcopal Church, Diocese of Michigan in June 1993 and March 2002.
The record group is open for research.
St. Thomas began as a mission Sunday School in Detroit, Michigan in 1883. In 1884 the Sunday School was transferred to a chapel at the corner of Shady Lane and West Grand Boulevard. In 1900 St. Thomas became a parish. New buildings were added and the parish thrived until the 1930s. After a long period of financial difficulties, St. Thomas reverted to mission status in 1963. In 1988 the church was forced to close due to declining membership. A complete history of St. Thomas is found in the folder titled "Background Materials."
The records of St. Thomas Episcopal Church document the history of an urban Detroit church and span the years 1885 to 1988. The record groups has been arranged into the following series: registers of baptisms, burials, marriages, communicants; registers of church services; vestry minute books; office files, and photograph albums.
Subjects:
Church records.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Detroit.; St. Thomas Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Churches.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Registers of baptisms, burials, marriages, communicants
  - Comprehensive registers
    - 1885-1900 (Box 1)
    - 1900-1904 (Box 1)
    - 1904-1913 (Box 1)
    - 1913-1924 (Box 2)
      (register of marriages only goes to 1920; thereafter record of marriages maintained in separate volume)
    - 1925-1977 (Box 2)
      (baptisms only go to 1956; thereafter record of baptisms maintained in separate volume)
  - Marriage register, 1920-1928 (Box 3)
  - Marriage register, 1928-1975 (Box 3)
  - Register of baptisms, 1955-1972; burials, 1954-1973; marriages (scattered), 1959-1972 and confirmations, 1956-1966 (Box 3)
  - Register of baptisms, 1980-1988 and burials, 1978-1986 (Box 3)
- Registers of church services
  - 1927-1938 (Box 4)
  - 1938-1977 (Box 4)
  - 1978-1988 (Box 4)
- Vestry Minute books
  The most important administrative records are the two volumes of vestry minutes dating from 1917 to 1923 and 1954 to 1968. Each of the volumes contains, in addition to minutes of the vestry, minutes of the bishop's committee records and of the annual parish meeting. The volume for the years 1954 to 1968 includes discussions the flight of many parishioners to the suburbs, the integration of minorities into the life of the parish, and specifics of the reversion of the church to mission status.
  - 1917-1923, (includes minutes of Annual Parish Meeting, treasurer's reports, and correspondence) (Box 5)
  - 1954-1968 (Box 5)
    (includes correspondence, senior warden's reports, and minutes of Bishop's Committee after reversion to mission status)
- Office files
  The office files include a miscellanea of scattered minutes and administrative papers. Of particular interest is the folder of material for Allen Grey. Mr. Grey held an office in St. Thomas from 1947 to 1982 and for most of that time served as senior warden. His correspondence contains both letters received and carbon copies of letters sent. The latter reveal, in colorful language, the thoughts and activities of a man passionately committed to his church and deeply concerned with the welfare of his fellow parishioners. This series also contains an Inventory of Furnishings and Memorials, created in 1966 by Winifred Gerow, who is identified in the photograph album as the historian of St. Thomas. The inventory was originally kept in a three ring binder. It is arranged chronologically by the object's date of acquisition or donation. Each page contains a description of an item and often includes interesting footnotes pertaining to its use or influence on parishioners or giving personal information about the donors.
  - Annual Parish Meeting Minutes, 1978-1984 (Box 5)
  - Background Materials (parish histories, clippings) (Box 5)
  - Bishop's Committee Minutes
    - 1975 (Box 5)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 5)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 5)
  - Budgets, 1981-1987 (Box 5)
  - General Correspondence, 1963-1984 (Box 5)
  - Grey, Allen (correspondence), 1947-1968 (Box 5)
  - Inventory of Furnishings and Memorials, 1966 with later additions
    - Introduction (parish history and chronology) (Box 5)
    - 1883-1890 (Box 5)
    - 1900-1903 (Box 5)
    - 1910-1925 (Box 5)
    - 1926-1939, (includes report of Annex Building Fund, 1927) (Box 5)
    - 1944-1956, (includes fund-raising pamphlet, 1956) (Box 5)
    - 1960-1965 and supplemental notes (Box 5)
  - Parish planning book, 1968-1972 (Box 5)
    (includes correspondence, and Bishop's Committee minutes)
  - Property Use Agreements
    - Adventist Church, Detroit Public Schools, 1980-1981 (Box 5)
    - Head Start Programs, 1978-1984 (Box 5)
      (includes correspondence)
    - Protestant Community Services, 1969-1971 (Box 5)
  - Treasurer's Annual Reports, 1974-1986 (Box 5)
- Photograph albums of church members and groups
  - 1950-1954 (Box 5)
  - 1955-1964 (Box 5)